Hello everybody, welcome back to the data structure and algorithms specialization.
こんにちは皆さん、データ構造とアルゴリズム専門科目の次の講義です。
Here I just want to give you a brief heads up,
ここではこれから2つのレクチャでお話をする内容についての
about what we're going to be talking about in the next two lectures.
ちょっとした注意点について話そうと思います。
So, in the next two lectures, we're going to dive right in.
これからすぐに入っていくことになる次の2つのレクチャでは、
We're going to look into a couple of algorithms problems, in particular
いくつかのアルゴリズム問題を見ていきます。特に、
we're going to talk about algorithms for computing Fibonacci numbers
フィボナッチ数を計算するアルゴリズムと、最大公約数を計算する
And algorithms for computing greatest common divisors.
アルゴリズムを見ていきます。
Now these might be, feel a little bit weird for
これらの問題は、現時点では、この講義で最初にお話しするアルゴリズムとしては
the very first algorithms that we're going to talk to in a class.
少し奇妙なようにも見えます。
They're kind of number theoretic and numerical, and they won't
これらの問題は数論的、数値的なもので、実は
actually be that similar to what we'll be talking about in the rest of the class.
これから先の講義で学習する予定のアルゴリズムとあまり似ていません。
So you might wonder why we're looking at them, and
だからなんでこんな問題を見るのか、また何に注目をすればいいのかを
what you should be paying attention to.
疑問に思うかもしれません。
And that's really what I  want to talk to you today about.
そこが、今日これから私が本当に話をしておきたいところなのです。
In particular, these two topics were chosen, because they were the clearest
特にこの2つのテーマが選ばれたのは、なぜアルゴリズムがきわめて重要なのか
examples we could think of for why algorithms are critically important.
ということをもっとも明らかにしてくれる例だからです。
Why coming up with a good algorithm is really so important on so many problems.
なぜよいアルゴリズムを見つけることがさまざまな問題に対してそんなに重要なのか。
And in particular,
そしてさらに、
both of these problems have the following very interesting properties.
この二つの問題は、両方とも次のような非常に興味深い特性を持っています。
To begin with, both of these problems have a pretty straightforward algorithm.
まずは、これらの問題は両方ともとてもストレートなアルゴリズムが解法として存在するということです。
One where you sort of take the definition of the problem that you're trying to
あなたが解こうとしている問題の定義自体からそのまま取り出せるような
solve.
ものです。
And from that you more or less immediately extract an algorithm.
その定義からそれなりに直接アルゴリズムを取り出すことが出来るのです。
You sort of take the words that you have, and
与えられている問題文から取り出して、
you sort of interpret them as an algorithm.
その取り出したものをアルゴリズムとして実装するのです。
And more or less immediately you have some code, and it works.
そして、それなりに素早く、ちゃんと動くコードを手に入れることが出来ます。
And it computes the things that you want it to compute.
そのコードはちゃんとあなたが計算したいことを計算してくれます。
Unfortunately, in both cases,
残念ながらどちらのケースも、
these very straightforward algorithms are far, far too slow.
これらの非常にストレートなアルゴリズムでは、まったく遅すぎます。
You end up with algorithms that take thousands of years to run,
実行に何千年もかかってしまうようなアルゴリズムしか得られないのです。
even on very modest inputs.
それほど多くない入力に対してもです。
And this is not acceptable for practical purposes,
実践的な目的にはこのような事態は受け入れられません。
you don't have millenia to wait for your computation to finish.
計算が完了するのに何千年も待つ時間なんてないんですから。
And so you need something better, and
なので、もっとよい解法が必要です。ここで、
it turns out in both of this cases there is something better.
両方のケースでもっとよい解法があるということを明らかにしていきます。
There is going to be a slightly more complicated algorithm,
もう少し複雑なアルゴリズムがあり、
something that maybe requires one or two bright ideas to get it to work.
それがちゃんと動かすのに、いくらかの妙案が必要となるようなものであるということを見ていきます。
This slightly more complicated algorithm, works fine and
このもう少し複雑なアルゴリズムは、ちゃんと動きますし、
is actually incredibly fast.
実はものすごく速いのです。
You can handle sort of any reasonable instance of these
これらの問題の妥当な入力量の例については、瞬きする間に
problems in the blink of an eye.
解くことが出来ます。
And so, the whole point of this is to really show with these very
つまり、この具体例で本当に説明したいポイントは、
concrete examples, that at least in these instances, and
少なくともこの実例、そして
in many others that we'll see throughout the course,
このコース全体で見るほかのさまざまな実例を通して伝えたいのは、
finding the right algorithm can make all the difference in the world.
アルゴリズムを発見するということは大きな違いを生むのだということです。
It's the difference between having an algorithm that
その違いとは、生きているうちに終わらないくらい
takes more time than you will have in your life to finish, and
時間のかかるアルゴリズムと、
an algorithm that is done before you even knew it started.
始まったかどうかわからないうちに終わってしまうアルゴリズムの差から出てきます。
And so really this is what you should be paying attention to.
つまり、これはあなたが注意を注がなければならないものなのです。
Why it is so, so important that we find good algorithms.
なぜよいアルゴリズムを探すということがそんなに大事なのか。
So that's what's coming up, I hope you enjoy the next couple of lectures.
それが次に出てくる話題です。次のレクチャーをお楽しみに。